Apologising is one of the first relationship skills we're taught as children.
道歉是我们小时候被教会的第一个人际关系技能。"
"Say sorry to your friend for stealing his toy", "Apologise to your mother for being so rude!"
把你偷玩具的事向你的朋友道歉"，"为你的粗鲁向你的母亲道歉！"
Children often apologise because they are told to by adults, regardless of whether they mean it, and the recipient is often told to forgive, regardless of whether they feel it.
孩子们常常因为被大人要求而道歉，不管他们是否真心实意，而接受道歉的一方也常常被告知要原谅，不管他们是否真的想原谅。
But the skill of making a heartfelt, genuine apology must grow as we become adults if we want to nurture healthy relationships.
但如果我们想要培养健康的人际关系，随着我们长大成人，做出真诚、由衷道歉的技能必须不断提升。
Dr. Aaron Lazare, psychiatrist and apology expert, says a good apology should have four elements.
精神病学家兼道歉专家亚伦·拉扎雷博士说，一个好的道歉应该包含四个要素。
The first is to acknowledge the offence and admit that you have wronged someone.
第一是承认错误，承认你错待了别人。
Next, there's an opportunity to explain what happened, without excusing yourself – in fact, it's sometimes best to simply say, "There's no excuse for my behaviour."
其次，有机会解释发生了什么，但不要为自己开脱——事实上，有时最好就说一句："我的行为没有任何借口。"
The third step is to express remorse and show that you understand how the behaviour has impacted the other person.
第三步是表达悔恨，并表明你理解自己的行为对他人造成了怎样的影响。
Lastly, offer to make amends.
最后，主动提出弥补。
If the mistake involved physical damage, have it repaired.
如果错误涉及物质损坏，就把它修好。
If it involved emotional pain, promise to be more sensitive in the future.
如果涉及情感上的伤害，就承诺将来更加谨慎。
Research shows that an apology is more effective when it is more costly to the apologiser, whether that's in terms of money, effort or time.
研究表明，道歉对道歉者付出的代价越高（无论是金钱、精力还是时间），道歉就越有效。
For example, a study called 'Do sincere apologies need to be costly?' found people were more convinced by an apology if the apologiser had to inconvenience themself in order to deliver the apology.
例如，一项名为《真诚的道歉需要付出代价吗？》的研究发现，如果道歉者为了道歉而不得不给自己带来不便，人们就会更加相信道歉。
For example, if that person made a journey to say sorry, rather than just waiting for the next meetup.
例如，如果那个人专门跑一趟去道歉，而不是等到下次见面再说。
A 2025 study called 'Sorries seem to have the harder words', found that people use longer words when apologising than when they're not apologising.
2025年一项名为《"对不起"似乎有更难的词》的研究发现，人们在道歉时使用的单词比不道歉时更长。
It also found that people perceived apologies with longer words as more apologetic than apologies with shorter words.
研究还发现，人们认为使用较长单词的道歉比使用较短单词的道歉更有歉意。
So, be sincere and own your mistakes, remembering that forgiveness can't be forced – the other person has the freedom to forgive or not to forgive.
所以，要真诚，承认自己的错误，记住原谅是不能强求的——对方有原谅或不原谅的自由。
But what's better: harbouring guilt for the rest of your life, or taking that weight off your shoulders?
但什么更好呢：一辈子心怀愧疚，还是卸下那个重担？